[SPEAKER_00]: This is in terms of self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's one of the extreme domains that the Buddha said one shouldn't go into.
[SPEAKER_01]: The other one is sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Usually, when a person hears that craving in terms of sensual activity is bad,
[SPEAKER_01]: the mind or that person swings to the opposite extreme of self-torture, thinking that self-torture is now the... that's what I should do.
[SPEAKER_01]: The belief that punishing the body will purify the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, yeah, if I just punish myself,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, feel pain now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, everything that I've done bad in the past, all these afflictions, my suffering will end.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will burn away all the past kind of consequences of consequences of my bad actions and end the suffering once and for all.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, the classic one would be sitting for long hours
[SPEAKER_01]: Trying not to move, staring at something until, you know, it's painful, but you just endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't eat, feel the hunger, you know, don't speak, don't see anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just shutting, trying to shut everything down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the Buddha says that this is not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll just actually read the definition.
[SPEAKER_01]: These two domains should not be gone to by one who has gone forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pursuit of happiness in sensual pleasures, the pursuit of self-mortification, both of which are ignoble and unbeneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without going to these domains, the Tathāgata has awakened to the middle way, which gives rise to peace, enlightenment, nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this self-mortification, that's a... it is a common reaction to giving up sensuality, or trying to give up sensuality, sensual activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do we know that we are actually not going into that domain?
[SPEAKER_01]: And actually... because giving up sensual activity is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that seems like self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe I should just give into sensuality a little bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, I think that's the...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a certain amount of information and knowledge and learning needs to take place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, I remember, I heard people say that before, that basically restraining, like being celibate, is a form of self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you have to endure your desires, therefore you're torturing yourself, therefore that's a wrong way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, the alternative to that is then sensuality, for that person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because... so they don't see anything in the middle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, you might feel like self-mortification initially, when you say no to your desires and take on training in the precepts, but you have to go through certain amount of withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you were dependent on certain types of drugs and so on, not taking them anymore will hurt for a bit,
[SPEAKER_00]: How long?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it depends how dependent you were.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you would... you would... well, you wouldn't... you would cease to suffer on account of withdrawal from those same things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how to differentiate mortification versus sensual indulgence?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, take on the precepts and don't take on any other observances that have nothing... that are not mentioned in the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just what's going to happen is, a mind of doubt is going to start besetting you, because you take on the precepts, you develop sense of a container, and so on, but then, yeah, sensuality would come back, desires would be prompted by sight sounds, smell, taste, touches, by this or that, and that would be painful, obviously, because you blocked the only outlet that you knew, which was acting out of its sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't want to stay with that pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only ways of getting rid of it is either give back to into sensuality and engage with it again, or perhaps try and get rid of the whole thing, which is always practically manifested through, oh, let me introduce more things that I want to do, more observances.
[SPEAKER_00]: More tightening, so that this state of mind that bothers me, affected with desire and doubt, so it doesn't come up at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how people fall into self-mortification and observances and being bound by Sīlabhāta Paramāsa.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because the pains of desires and hindrances that are revealed through training in the precepts and sense restraint, they don't want to bear them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't want to stay with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They want to get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as I said, since the only way of getting rid of it before was giving in to them, now you stop doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now the only way to get rid of it is, okay, let me do more of other things that would, you know, prevent this from arising in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you end up, like, adding observances, adding the duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: All because you don't want to stay with the mind states that were revealed through keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's really what training in the precepts mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Staying with the mind states that are revealed through keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you start to train in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not meant to shelter you from those mind states.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're meant to simply not make it worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not allow the mind to escape you towards sense objects in the way it used to when you started acting out and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But...
[SPEAKER_00]: Once the mind is contained, once the the pressures, the desires, the cravings are contained through the prism, they're going to feel unpleasant, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the training now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Staying with that, now trying to introduce more rules, more techniques, so that it doesn't come up at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want it to come up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will come up, whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to run away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to learn how to become immovable in face of it, while it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how, then, you will truly not be touched.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if a person is suffering, they either try to get rid of that suffering through sensual activity?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You give in to sensuality to get rid of the pain of the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if the desire were not unpleasant, you would have absolutely... it would be inconceivable to seek the sense objects and proliferate and engage with bodily pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because desire is unpleasant, that's why you head in that direction as a default.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you stop doing that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you still act out in another way, which is, kind of, try to... okay, it's self-torture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, you have the extreme examples of, I'll just try and destroy the senses, so that then these mind states that I have to endure, I don't have to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll crush it, kind of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you... if you... somebody doesn't go that... in that coarse manner, try to destroy the senses or starve them out or something, they would still then, oh, well, let me do more things
[SPEAKER_00]: So that senses will not come across anything that can provoke the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is just, as I said, kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, you will have... you will be doing that to some extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to protect your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the purpose of the sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how far you start taking that,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to determine whether you are now crossing into the domain of self-mortification, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: just trying to manage the senses, so that the mind states don't come up, because you don't want to have to endure them and deal with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the fundamental difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a person can choose to restrain their sight, what they look at, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, inevitably, things will come within range, you'll see it, and the mind will be provoked.
[SPEAKER_00]: The provoked mind is unpleasant, feels unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to stay with that particular type of discomfort, the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead, you know, well, like the sutta says, let me... those other... let me not see the sights like a blind man.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, let me pull my eyes out.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, you'll stop seeing the sights, but the mind remained equally untrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, you even lost one of the means of accessing that untrained mind, revealing that untrained mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's important that you have to recognize... what you have to recognize is that you... it's important to not act out of the intention towards sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: But at the same time, not to try and destroy the eyes, because you want the non-intentional sights to provoke your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the training will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you have no intention to look, smell, taste, touch towards any sensual objects, yet they come in the range, and yet the wild animal is provoked.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, oh, that's what...
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the nature of the senses and the untrained mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the difference that training in the virtue will reveal, how your intention matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether the provocation came on account of you intentionally provoking it, intentionally looking, intentionally tasting, touching, smelling and so on, or unintentionally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first, you have to completely abandon the intentional provocation, intentional adding of the fuel, so that then you can discern the unintentional, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of the unintentional environment, so to speak, that then your mind reacts to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that's where the training, that's where the communication can occur.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but again, if you don't know that, you would then think that's a problem as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it hurts, because it's unpleasant, because desire, pressure is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's... and because of that, you want to get rid of that as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let me then go on top of a mountain, pull my eyes out, block my ears, never see, smell, taste, touch, and I'll be safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just gonna destroy the means of revealing the untrained mind, the five senses, and yet the mind will remain equally trained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or let me focus hard on some concentration technique where I'll stop perceiving any senses, anything that comes, and that's the peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's just shutting down.
[SPEAKER_00]: The peace is when no amount of sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, unintentional or intentional for that matter, can provoke the mind towards desire, ill-will or distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, in order to get to that point, first you have to stop doing all the intentional acts towards those unwholesome things, in order to reveal the unintentional provocations on account of the wild mind, in order to calm it down.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the mind is fully calmed, trained, properly understood, then intentional or unintentional, it's all pure anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all purified anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's aversion, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Towards what you're experiencing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is a sutta where the Buddha says that, you know, as a bodhisattva, as he was beginning to train, he thought, pleasure is not to be reached through pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, freedom from dukkha is not to be reached through pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure is to be reached through pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what he thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if I just...
[SPEAKER_00]: If I just inflict the pain, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, eventually, it will get to this nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but it depends what type of pain we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can have a pain of just bearing the elements, bearing the discomfort, bearing the power of your determination, sticking to it, and that will not necessarily result in anything, anything of value.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have, as I said, a particular type of pain that's not terribly unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Particular type of pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Particular type of pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pain of the recognition of the untrained mind from within, that you are containing, but not trying to kill or suffocate either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like the pain of that mind, of that pressure, and then another pain that comes on top of it is the recognition of, oh, this needs to be tamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where do I even begin?
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, the doubt, now the pain of doubt, the pain of not knowing whether it works, whether not, where does sensory strain lead, and so... All of that, it's a lot harder to stick to, in terms of training and practice, than, oh, just tell me a technique that I will mindlessly adhere to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, I won't have to think about anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: That there's a reason these techniques are popular and are mainstream.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, they feed into that very thing of, okay, so if I just adhere to this mechanical precepts, repetition, doing this or that, I don't have to feel the the life of this wild animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can just keep, as it comes up, I could just keep putting new things on top of it, more and more, and with a hope that eventually it will stop coming up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the measure, the longer I do it, the harder I do it, it's going to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: The stiffer it is, the more rigid it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, so it means that pain, purification comes through... Well, patient endurance, that khanti.
[SPEAKER_01]: Patient endurance of what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not of anything that you think of or feel dutiful towards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Patient endurance of the states of the mind that come up as a result of you imposing virtue and sense restraint as a form of training.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when... See, you could say there is a desire to look or taste something, and then you said no to yourself, because it was against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, maybe it wasn't against the precepts, but it was clearly rooted in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say you wanted to eat something that was unnecessary, and you wanted to increase... you want to start practicing sense restraint, and you said no to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now,
[SPEAKER_00]: That desire, the mind of that desire, it's gonna rebel.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gonna... it's gonna complain about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gonna try and attack you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gonna try and get you back under its will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's not pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just from inside.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like you're being... being basically threatened from inside.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the right training means staying with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not acting out of it, but not trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, as I said, it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unpleasant in a very specific kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: A specific kind that nobody will accidentally choose to adopt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody will accidentally choose to stay with that particular level of discomfort that your own mind threatens you and so on with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead, it's a lot easier than, say, you said no to this desire, now there's a... the mind of desire comes up, or let me now
[SPEAKER_00]: Focus on my breathing, or do this technique, or watch my sensations, or, in other words, let me distract myself with anything else now, all the other things that are on paper said as wholesome, so that this mind goes away.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it might work, and it might work once, twice, it might work ten times, but you always have to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever the mind comes up, you always have to calm it down, because you don't know how to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the problem is not that
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I want to calm the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the problem is that you're basically believing that you need to act and... and... and suppress.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind states that are revealed on account of restraint and virtue carries the implicit view that will then prevent you from uprooting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, prevent you from actually addressing the problem, so that the mind will... mind in itself will stop having the desire to pressure you with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if there is... if the mind itself has lost the desire towards things you said no to, that's the true calming.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the true non-disturbance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the animal is not reactive anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It does not attack anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to practice keeping the leash and restraining it and suffocating it and holding it down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the virtue did that for you, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It revealed the state of how deeply the animal was untrained, how wild it was.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, do you do more things so you don't have to do that work of training it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you recognize that the real training is, okay, the mind of desire is present, okay, the wild animal is here,
[SPEAKER_00]: If I try to run away from it, act out of it, none of that will result in communicating the right things to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first and foremost, I have to acknowledge that that's the state of mind for what it is and stay with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Know it as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why in that other sutta, when somebody asked the Buddha, you know, Master Gautama said that dhamma is directly visible here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: How should that be understood?
[SPEAKER_00]: And people would, you know, often think how directly visible the here and now, the present moment, awareness, all sorts of mystical ideas about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha didn't answer any of that in that manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, well, when you know the mind of lust as mind of lust, a mind of aversion as mind of aversion, that's how dhamma is directly visible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because, you know, I can contemplate the Four Noble Truths, and the Eightfold Path, and the Paticca Upāda, or, as I say, go in the mystical direction and just start describing it in some, who knows, idiosyncratic terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognizing the mind for what it is, as it is such, staying with it, is how you practice the dhamma, how you get to see the dhamma directly visible here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Four Noble Truths, see the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, everything else follows from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the recognition of the mind states that come as a result of the restraint, virtue, and so on, that's how you get to practice the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you get to see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you get to see the principle behind that whole training that we described.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the self-mortification would always, as I said, would always kind of... it could have these, obviously, coarse extremes, but it actually goes as far as you have a mind state that has a reason, you don't want it, you're aversive towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to get rid of this mind because it hurts me and that's why I hate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're acting out of aversion now.
[SPEAKER_00]: First, you want to act out of essential desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: You said no to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, there is a painful mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you want to get rid of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, oh, so now you're going to the aversion direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just wanted to get rid of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Adopting sets of behaviors, rules, duties, techniques to get rid of it, to keep the lid on it, to keep it down, so you don't have to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a form of self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you believe that by adhering to a certain
[SPEAKER_00]: Technique, or just mindless adherence to the duty, or what Ajahn says, and I don't have to think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That will free my mind from these wild tendencies.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can... and you can keep the lid forcefully.
[SPEAKER_00]: For decades, if you want, the day will come when you forget about the lid, when you won't close it properly, for one reason or the other, and the same wild animal is going to come out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because nothing has changed in terms of its internal tendencies.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the deer herd sutta that we mentioned so many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, they shun the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: They shun the pressure of the bait, the proximity of the bait, and run into the mountains.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, they're safe there, and then they run out of food there, and they come back, because they have to eat sooner or later.
[SPEAKER_00]: They come back, and they still didn't learn how to differentiate the bait, and not act towards the bait, and they get, again, hooked, caught, and then Māra does with them what he wants.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that you have to keep a lid on things means, and you're running away, that that whole state means that you're running away from something, there's something you're keeping a lid on that hasn't changed at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you keep the lid on things because you recognize, well, I need to keep the lid on things for now, but you don't confuse that for the actual
[SPEAKER_00]: Training of that which is underneath the lid.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I'm trying to cover it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you will be keeping the lid on things one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what I'm talking about here, it's now when you develop a view that keeping the lid on the wild mind is something that will magically just result in that mind not being wild anymore, eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, so, uh, just to...
[SPEAKER_01]: One suffers, and then you get... you just... you choose the path of punishing yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if I feel that I punish myself, then things will be okay, in some sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a classic example would be, like, I break the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: I try and keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: I break the precepts, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: I...
[SPEAKER_01]: I lied to someone, or whatever, sexual activity, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You feel guilty on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you then determine, well, that guilt is, you know, suffering, and I shouldn't do that, and that was wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I will not eat for... Next ten days.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, next ten days, I'm not going to eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not going to look at anybody.
[SPEAKER_00]: To purify myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're trying to make this... That's apples and oranges, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, nothing to do with one another.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just to say, it's kind of trying to make a deal, like you determining what the price is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then making a deal with yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, that's a good deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you, thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can do that, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you start doing that, just the more pain you feel for not eating, you think that this is paying for what I've done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I'm paying, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But who are you to... Who are you to decide the price, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're in no position, because you're the one that owes the money.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is, you break the precepts, you fail, you acknowledge that to that extent, you confess it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Guilt comes up, you don't try to get rid of the guilt.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it comes up on account of... like rational guilt.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it comes up on account of you factually breaking the precepts, well, let it sink in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, if the mind starts revolving around it irrationally, well, you recognize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still don't try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just restrain your mental input towards the irrational guilt.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't try to get rid of the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you learn from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how the Buddha would say, like, yes, transgressing and then confessing it, recognizing your fault to that extent, is how you grow in this training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not beating yourself up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, or like not confessing, and then just doing some random things as a penance.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, you know where the penance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bringing it out to the light.
[SPEAKER_00]: Acknowledging it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and it's like, if I act out of lust, well, the only way that I'm going to really pay for it, so to speak, and overcome the consequences of all my lustful actions,
[SPEAKER_01]: To me, the only thing that you would do is to uproot the lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uproot the lust, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you never do it again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would mean that you are...
[SPEAKER_00]: Truly rehabilitated.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rehabilitated, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are... That's like the confession, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I acted out of lust because I...
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to act out of lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I still maintain that lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if I'm really sorry, then I should give up lust forever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the actual purity comes from.
[SPEAKER_00]: The purity of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're actually uprooting the lust, not just adhering to the traditional observances and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, you know, I never break the precepts, I'm pure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, you never break the precepts means you're not making things worse, but you're far from pure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, precepts prevent you from adding, as we said before, adding fuel to that fire, but they do not
[SPEAKER_00]: They do not uproot the problem in and of themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to make the effort and tame that animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, fully uproot and extinguish those desires of that untrained wild mind and all those tendencies that it has, by containing it, by staying with it, by seeing through it, by presenting it with right perceptions at the right time, all the other, like, higher modes of training that we have talked about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Discerning anicca...
[SPEAKER_00]: Discerning anicca, unattractiveness, loving-kindness, all those things that you would be bringing to the mind, depending on its state, in order for you to communicate to it, to teach it.